Previously on Gotham...
GORDON: Word
of the chemical spill
- reached the mainland.
- Reunification
isn't happening.
No action until the government
can determine if Gotham's safe.
OSWALD: I sentence
you, Victor Zsasz, to die.
- (gunshot)
- (gasping, screaming)
Get him out of there!
What the hell are you doing?!
Trying to keep you all from
making a terrible mistake.
- Her name is Ivy.
- She's a witch.
I'm feeding the earth with
these wretched creatures.
It consumes them,
and then it flourishes.
We wouldn't have
escaped without you.
You saved me
and my friends.
I wanted to help.
- Come with us.
- Are you telling me
you found a way out of Gotham?
It's a submarine.
I've been giving you space,
but we have to talk about
how this is gonna work.
I'm gonna be a
part of this kid's life.
- Oh, you seem pretty confident
about that.
- I am.
You're having a
baby with Barbara.
Can't change the past, so...
I guess we just
have to live with it.
(indistinct chatter)
Come on, people!
Time's a-wastin'!
The filtration system that
Lucius designed is working.
What you're doing is both
unnecessary and it's reckless.
Our supplies of drinking
water are at critical levels.
Every day, the gangs
grow more aggressive.
If I can get a cease-fire,
even a temporary one,
then when reunification
does happen,
at least there will be
people left to save.
They deserve that much.
And does your child
deserve a father?
You have no problem
taking care of the entire city.
What about focusing
on just one life?
(sighs) Why are
you always so ready
to put yourself
in the crosshairs?
It's like you won't be satisfied
until you sacrifice yourself.
You really believe that?
I do.
And it scares me.
How is this gonna work?
Am I supposed to
just stay at home
and raise this
child with Barbara
while you go cowboying
off all the time?
It won't always be like this.
After reunification...
Nothing will be different.
Unless you stop being...
Me?
BULLOCK: Hey, Jim.
(exhales) I have to go.
- We'll talk after.
- If there is an after.
- (shouting)
- (chainsaw buzzing)
Oh, yeah?! Oh-ho!
Oswald, where the hell is Nygma?
Shouldn't we have
left the city already?
Ms. Kean,
this may come as a surprise,
but building a
submarine from scratch
by yourself takes time.
- Patience.
- Easy for you to say.
You're not a walking egg timer.
Tell him to get a move on.
And why, exactly,
are you hosting Gordon's
gangland get-together?
Keep your friends close and
your enemies closer, my dear.
If we're really going
to leave Gotham,
we need to keep Gordon happy.
You know all about
that, don't you?
It was a momentary slip.
The world was on fire.
(loud thump)
(indistinct shouting)
OSWALD: Jim,
it's your show.
Mi casa, su casa.
I'll make this short.
Gotham is running dry.
Our supply of clean water
will only last a
few more months.
So you have a choice.
You can keep killing each other,
fighting over what
little water is left,
maybe eke out a few
more months, then die.
Or...
we can all agree right now
to an immediate cease-fire.
(scoffing, chattering)
(speaks indistinctly)
The government will
not annex a war zone.
If we can show them that we
deserve to rejoin the mainland,
supply chain will be restored
and we will all survive
until reunification.
That's the choice.
Life or death.
Your call.
(indistinct chatter)
(chatter stops)
- (gunshot)
- (gasping)
Weapons down!
Get back!
Jim, you see where
the shooter was?
Jim.
Oh, my God.
♪♪
- (indistinct chatter)
- (labored breathing)
BULLOCK: Get back!
You're gonna be all right.
It's bad. We got
to move him. Now.
Clinic's too far. M.E.'s office.
Alvarez, come on. Help.
On it.
Take my gun.
- (groaning)
- One, two, three.
All right. Get back.
- Back! Get back!
- (shouting)
Well,
I did not see that coming.
- (siren wailing in distance)
- (bell clanging)
What made you choose this,
of all places,
for a scavenging mission?
Just trust me, okay?
What the hell?
("Cherry Blossom Moon" by
Rob Parton Orchestra playing)
Sit.
(chuckles)
(chuckles softly)
Wow.
Candles.
If I didn't know any better,
I'd say this was a... date.
Maybe it is.
That okay with you?
Maybe.
Good.
So let's eat.
Lee!
It's Jim. He's lost
a lot of blood.
Can you save him?
(exhales)
Come with me!
(indistinct chatter)
Doc says he's gonna be okay.
He's gonna pull through.
But until then,
I'm acting captain.
Now, the gangs of this city
think this is their time
that they can run wild!
They are dead wrong!
I want us to take
to the streets.
It is show-of-force time!
We ain't gonna give 'em an inch!
Harper,
I want you to
organize patrol teams.
What are you gonna do?
I'm gonna find out
who shot my partner.
THOMPKINS: The bullet
shattered against a rib.
I have to get all
the fragments out.
(exhales)
I haven't done general
surgery since med school.
There.
All right, there's
an exit wound,
so the rest must've
gone through.
I need to sew him up.
Can you get my kit?
Right away.
Come on, Jim.
(distantly): You can do
this, but you have to fight.
You hear me?
You have to fight.
♪♪
(gavel banging)
JUDGE: Order in the court.
James Gordon,
you have been brought here
to be judged for
your many crimes,
and your very life
hangs in the balance.
Do you understand?
No, I...
The defendant understands
and waives his right
to appeal.
The trial of James Gordon
will now begin.
No! Wait!
- (siren wailing in distance)
- (dog barking)
That...
was the best canned
meal I've ever had.
And if this was a date,
I don't know how
you're gonna top it
when everything
gets back to normal.
I don't think things are
ever gonna be normal.
For me, anyways.
What do you mean?
Wayne Manor's gone.
And I know that a lot
of people lost a lot more,
but part of me
wonders if it wasn't fate.
(sighs) It wasn't.
It was Jeremiah
blowing up your house.
Maybe it's time to move on.
You mean, like, leave Gotham?
Bruce, forget Wayne Manor.
This city is your home.
And how many terrible
things have happened to it
because of me?
Galavan.
Ra's al Ghul.
If this city really is my home,
then maybe the best thing
I can do for it is leave.
I have to say...
kind of agree with
you on that one,
billionaire boy.
OSWALD: Jim Gordon's
blood on my floor.
(groans) Olga!
Why is the help never
around when you need them?
(chuckling)
This could be good for us.
You especially.
Are you serious?
Your baby daddy is
the top cop in Gotham.
A dead Jim Gordon
is the only way
you can hold
on to your little...
bundle of joy.
Harvey, how is our dear...
(grunts, gasps)
Who the hell did it?!
If I find out it was you,
I swear to God...
It wasn't me! I merely
supplied the venue!
At your boss's request!
That doesn't mean squat!
Fine. You want to
know who's to blame?
James Gordon!
He invited every
criminal in Gotham!
What did he think
was gonna happen?
(grunts, coughs)
How about you, huh?
When did you two
become so... buddy-buddy?
Maybe when you hatched up a plan
so you could keep
that baby for yourself.
Harvey, whatever
you think of me,
I did not plot to kill
my child's father.
Well, someone here did!
Someone in this
room shot Jim Gordon,
and I'm not leaving
till I find out who it was!
Wrong! The shooter was not here!
Look at the window, stupid!
The shot came from outside.
If the shooter was there...
and the trajectory was here...
Jim was...
then the bullet...
Uh-huh.
I'm gonna find out who this was,
and when I do, there's
gonna be hell to pay.
Harvey.
Is there anything I can do?
Yeah. You can keep the
gangs from tearing the city apart.
(door closes)
What do you want?
You...
I will deal with later.
I'm here...
for you.
I need you to come with me.
Why would I do that?
Because you love me so much.
Well, not yet, but you will.
Don't mess with him, Ivy.
Protecting your boyfriend?
That's cute.
But I thought that
might happen, so...
I brought a friend.
I stumbled across
this charming man
on the way over here,
and apparently, you
two know each other.
Leave her out of this!
You know, I heard you talking
about the future of Gotham...
but Gotham will
be what I decide.
A green world.
Won't that be beautiful?
(whispers): Gorgeous.
(chuckles)
Bruce and I have to go.
You always did think
you were better than me.
But without my plants,
you never would
have left your bed.
I made you strong again.
Think about that
while my friend is
cutting out your heart.
♪♪
(seabirds squawking)
There are so many things
I wish I could say to you.
(monitor beeping steadily)
So many things I
wish we could do.
This can't be the end.
Come on, Jim.
Talk to me.
Say something.
Speak.
- (gavel striking slowly,
rhythmically)
- No.
This isn't right. I
shouldn't be here.
- JUDGE: Silence! Silence!
- You have to listen to me.
The prosecution will now
give its opening remarks.
Your Honor, Jim Gordon's
crimes are a matter of public record.
He's failed Gotham
at every turn.
He failed to
clean up the city...
failed to stop the bridges
from being destroyed,
failed to protect those
poor, innocent souls
in the refuge he
himself created...
Haven.
I tried.
- I did the best...
- Silence!
(gavel bangs)
One more outburst and
you will be held in contempt.
I'm hurt.
I need help. Please.
Continue.
The issue here is not
how many people have died
because of Jim Gordon,
but how many more must die
in order to satisfy
his need to be a hero.
Therefore we pose
one simple question:
Are the people in
Jim Gordon's life
better off with him alive
or dead?
I think I'm dying.
PROSECUTOR: The
prosecution would like to call
its first witness, Your Honor.
Dr. Lee Thompkins.
♪♪
(rapid beeping)
Come on, Jim.
Hold on.
(door opens)
How is he?
Touch and go.
(sighs): He's stable for now.
I removed all the
bullet fragments,
but something keeps
pulling him down.
Where are the fragments?
(monitor beeping steadily)
What is it?
"V.Z."
Victor Zsasz.
(horn honks in distance)
Okey-dokey.
Time to boogie.
♪♪
ZSASZ: Hey!
I'm only here for Gordon.
So all of you stay down.
'Cause I see anyone...
and, you know...
bang.
Oi, oi!
Now, I heard you were
looking for Jim Gordon.
(weakly): Uh-huh.
Listen, I know we have history.
Let's just let
bygones be bygones.
Yeah, right.
You did this to my face.
Whatever.
It's not like you were much
of a looker before, anyway.
(growls) Ivy says
you hurt her feelings.
Why would you do that!?
She's so sweet!
(roaring)
Ivy didn't make me strong.
I made me strong.
(grunts, chokes)
Tell me where she took Bruce.
The only reason I'm
not ending you right now
is the thought of
the look on your face
when Jim Gordon
walks through that door.
Because he's alive,
you son of a bitch!
Ugh. What did you eat?
You smell like a butcher.
You know, I'm vegan now.
Why kill Jim now?
Makes no sense.
He saved your miserable ass.
He prevented Penguin
from executing you.
If anyone, you should
be going after Cobblepot.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Maybe I'll do him next.
It's kind of not up to me.
You're working for someone?
(whispers): Oh.
Sorry.
(grunting)
I want a name!
Ah, what's in a name?
A rose by any other name
would smell as sweet.
You know, I'm
really taking the time
to stop and smell
the roses these days.
Like, actual roses.
They're great.
Are you high?
On love.
But like I said...
my lips are sealed.
(snaps fingers) Ivy Pepper.
You said it, not me.
Uh, I'm technically
not allowed to say it.
Her name. Which
is such a bummer,
because it's the most
beautiful name in the world.
You watch him.
I could say it all day.
Hey, I will say it all day.
Ivy.
Ivy Pepper.
Mrs...
Ivy Pepper Zsasz.
Oh, that sounds good.
Here you are, Miss Thompkins.
Careful, it's...
a little bit hot.
Forgive me, but I...
heard on the grapevine
that you and Captain Gordon
had a rather heated
exchange this morning.
Oh, God.
Was it that bad?
Apparently, it
was like a session
of the Italian parliament.
(sighs heavily)
You have misgivings
about the arrival of
this child, don't you?
What am I getting
myself into, Alfred?
How am I supposed
to raise a child
alongside a psychopath
like Barbara Kean?
I mean, how the hell
is this gonna work?
But... but that's not all of it.
If Jim and I are gonna do this,
then we have to do it together.
You know how he is.
I don't know what's going on
inside that man's
head sometimes.
I think you'll find
that he needs you
a lot more than he's letting on.
Well, I need to
hear it from him.
I never thought that this was
how my life was going to be.
I have no interest in
being a father myself.
I always presumed
that I was unfit to be one.
And then I found myself...
one night staring down
an alley at this little boy
quite literally
shaking with fear.
I don't know, it's funny,
isn't it, what life throws you?
I'm keenly aware that I am not
Master Bruce's flesh and blood.
But it's the moments.
The little things, like...
like when he uses a skill
that I once taught him,
or we laugh at a joke
that only he and I share.
Those have been some of the
most ecstatic moments of my life.
Nothing can possibly
prepare you for that joy.
The hows and the whats...
you'll figure that stuff out.
What matters is this:
you'll be an exquisite mother,
and that child, he or
she will be extraordinary...
because of you.
♪♪
(sniffles)
Thank you, Alfred.
Jim, can you hear me?
I'm right here,
right next to you.
Can you feel me?
Lee?
Dr. Lee Thompkins.
You've suffered at this man's
hands more than anyone.
Broken heart,
broken engagement.
A lost child.
And yet, you're still with him.
I love him.
After all the pain
he's caused you,
would your life be better,
could it not still be better,
without Jim Gordon?
Answer the question.
- Lee?
- PROSECUTOR: I'll ask it
a different way.
Would you, Dr. Lee Thompkins,
be better off if Jim
Gordon were dead?
I'm sorry.
Everything he touches dies.
Prosecution rests, Your Honor.
You made her say that.
PROSECUTOR: I didn't
make her say anything.
Ask them.
(whooshing, flames hissing)
GORDON: Who are they?
PROSECUTOR: More people
who trusted you, who believed you
when you said you
would protect them.
They're from Haven.
I think I'm dying.
And isn't it about time?
The verdict's in.
You're guilty.
(wind whistling)
Hey, Jeff, listen to me.
One day, you're
gonna meet someone
who's gonna totally
change your life,
and that's gonna make you happy,
and you deserve it.
Or not.
Is she here?
She's here, isn't she?
Sweetie.
All I asked of you
was to kill Jim Gordon.
You're not angry, are you?
'Cause I'll do it.
I'll do it right now.
I'll do it.
You keep the cops busy.
Luckily, the other part of my
plan is coming together nicely.
(steam hissing)
Lucius!
Bruce.
I had no idea you
were stopping by.
I wanted to check
on your progress.
Well, the toxicity levels in
this river continue to drop.
At this point, we'll be under
the threshold mandated
by the government
sooner than expected.
It's not glamorous
work, but we are helping
to save the lives of
thousands of people.
People. Ugh.
I'm sorry. Did you
just say "People. Ugh"?
Lucius, what if I
were to tell you
I have in my possession
the most intoxicating perfume
you'll ever smell?
I would tell you that's
an abrupt change of topic.
Can we go back to the part
where you said "People. Ugh"?
(grunts)
Mmm.
(echoing): Oh, my... goodness.
Lucius,
Ivy sent me here to get
you to shut down the plant.
Can you do that for her?
(distorted): For Ivy? Anything.
She is so great.
♪ They say, they say
she's got to grow up ♪
♪ And they say, they
say she's got to get a job ♪
♪ I know, I know I'll
never be like the rest ♪
♪ Of the bunch. Oh! ♪
Raise your glasses.
I called you all here today
because Jim Gordon
is at death's door.
ALL: Yeah!
For years, he has hounded us,
beaten us, shot us.
And today, he got his due.
To Jim Gordon.
May he rot in hell!
ALL: Yeah!
♪♪
What exactly are you doing?
I'm trying to keep this
city from ripping itself apart.
So this has nothing to do
with your feelings for Jim?
What if Ed fails, and
we are stuck here?
This will put us in
Gordon's good graces.
Consider it a backup plan.
♪♪
Listen up!
Now to the real reason
I brought you all here.
I want you
to agree to an immediate truce.
(laughing): Get out of here.
And what if, instead, we
shoot you and take your club?
I don't think so.
See, those drinks
I just gave you...
They're poisoned.
And you had two shots
before everyone got here.
So that should be
taking effect around...
(muffled groaning)
(choking)
- (indistinct muttering)
- now.
The rest of you have 48
hours before you'll need
the antidote, which
I will deliver to you,
provided you go
back to your territories,
play nice, and send
me all your guns. Deal?
I said, "Deal?"
(all voicing assent)
- Now get out of here!
- MAN:
All right.
- Yeah. Out.
- Come on.
Hmm.
Jim will be so pleased.
Keep your friends close,
and your enemies closer.
Isn't that right... Pengy?
Once I reverse the system,
all the toxin we pulled from
the river will be rereleased,
and the overload
should destroy the filters.
In a matter of minutes,
the entire facility
will be inoperable.
There.
- (alarms sounding)
- Perfect.
Ivy's gonna be so happy.
You think so?
MAN (over P.A.):
Security breach. Zone 1.
That's odd.
Selina.
I'll take care of it.
Okay.
All right, listen up!
I know you're probably
familiar with Ivy Pepper.
In fact, you were probably here
when she hypnotized the
whole frigging precinct, okay?
She is on the loose,
and we've got to find
her and take her down.
Actually, fellas,
- she's already here!
- (gun chamber clicking)
(indistinct shouting)
That's right. Ivy
came and freed me.
That is true love for you.
She really understands
what makes me tick.
- Don't worry, though.
- (yells)
I'm just a distraction
so she can finish off
Jim once and for all.
You know, that's how
great couples work.
Maybe I shouldn't
have told you that.
Oh, well.
(distant, rapid gunfire)
- I'm sorry,
Miss Thompkins.
- I know. Go.
Thank you, Alfred.
Come on, Jim.
Can you hear me?
Stay with me.
(echoing): Stay with me, Jim.
(indistinct chatter)
BULLOCK: Jim!
(laughs) Want a drink?
Alvarez makes a
hell of a Mai Tai.
I can barely feel my face.
Harvey, what is this?
It's your wake.
Pretty nice turn-out, huh?
♪ For he's a jolly good fellow ♪
- ♪ For he's a jolly good ♪
- GORDON:
Stop.
♪ Fellow ♪
♪ For he's a jolly good fellow ♪
(snorting)
(scattered laughter)
♪ Which nobody can deny. ♪
(laughter)
Wake?
(piano continues playing tune)
I'm not dead yet.
Well, be a little
bit of a bummer
to have it after you
died, don't you think?
I'm gonna have a kid, Harvey.
How do I protect that child
when everything around me dies?
Harvey?
WILL: That's a good question.
Will.
You said I'd be safe in Haven.
I trusted you.
I know.
I did my best.
Your best never
seems good enough.
It's time to go.
- (beeping)
- THOMPKINS:
No, no, no.
- No, no, no, no. Jim.
- (long, continuous beep)
- Where's my adrenaline?
- (distant, rapid gunfire)
Oh...
Oh, looks like Victor
succeeded after all.
I guess I'll have to
settle for killing you.
I can tell you one thing.
I am sick and tired of getting
shot at in my own precinct.
Hey, what the
bloody hell's going on?
I thought you had
this lunatic locked up.
Ivy broke him out and
gave him an arsenal.
But I have an idea. I got to get
to the storeroom. Give me cover.
Alvarez, go!
(grunts)
(grunting)
(gasps)
(panting)
Why are you doing this?
What has Jim ever done to you?
Gotham has a chance
to be born anew.
To return to what it was
before people ripped down the
trees and paved over the earth.
He's trying to reunify
with the mainland
to save all these people.
A return to filth.
Pollution.
He's fighting for
death, while I...
promise life...
in its purest form.
Is that your plan?
To have the plants take
over Gotham by killing Jim?
Oh, killing Gordon's
just the first part.
Bruce Wayne is
taking care of the rest.
- For what it's worth,
I am sorry.
- For what?
(gasping breath)
This pain is nothing
compared to what
you are about to feel.
Say good-bye... to
Jim Gordon for me.
No!
No, no, no, no, no!
Jim.
Selina, you're wasting
your time.
Bruce, you have to
snap out of Ivy's spell.
- This is not you.
- You're wrong.
Ivy's given me a purpose.
(grunting)
Stop! Stop! I don't
want to fight you!
What are you gonna do?
Kill everything in Gotham?
The toxins will only
kill all the people.
The plants will
adapt; they always do.
- Can you hear what
that sounds like?
- Yeah.
It sounds great!
(coughing)
(panting)
I guess I shouldn't
be surprised.
You don't care about Gotham.
You're gonna leave anyway.
What about the rest of us, huh?
The ones who are gonna be
stuck here without you?!
Selina...
(both gasping for breath)
Selina... I'm okay.
- Bruce, I'm so sorry.
- We got to stop
Lucius.
- Come on.
- Okay.
(grunts)
(alarm blaring)
Lucius! You have
to stop the shutdown.
Oh, no, I can't do that.
Ivy will be so mad.
Listen to me, I-I used Ivy's
perfume to hypnotize you.
She's using you.
No.
Ivy would never do that.
We're perfectly bonded,
like... carbon and oxygen
or hydrogen
- and oxygen...
- We do not have time
for this.
I'm sorry.
(grunts)
- (flips switch)
- There.
Oh, you kicked me in the head.
I didn't have a choice, Lucius.
Bruce, where's Ivy?
She was headed to the GCPD.
I wonder what Ivy's
doing right now.
BULLOCK: Hey, lover boy.
Are you serious right now?
As a heart attack.
(chuckles)
What an idiot.
- (Bullock yelling)
- Oh, my...
(grunts)
Ah, that felt good.
Come on, Jim.
You fight for everyone
else. You never give up.
Fight for yourself,
Jim. Come on!
(thunder crashing)
(door creaking)
It's time.
(thunder crashing)
THOMPKINS (echoing): Jim.
Lee.
Is that...?
Yes.
Do you want to...?
I don't know.
I don't know that I can.
Oh, I see.
- No!
- Good-bye, Jim.
No!
I want to live!
It's too late.
No! I want to live!
(screaming)
(monitor beeping rapidly)
(baby bawling)
(gasping breaths)
(beeping slows)
(gasping breath) Lee.
Don't move. Don't move.
How do you feel?
Like I almost died.
Well, you didn't.
You fought. You came back to me.
Because I need you.
Lee...
- this child...
- It's okay.
It's okay to be scared.
The only thing
scarier than doing this
is doing it without you.
Can I ask you something?
♪♪
(bell tolling)
(indistinct chatter)
BRUCE: He seems nervous.
SELINA: I know.
He should be thrilled.
Marrying a woman who's smarter
and better-looking than him.
Selina, while we were fighting,
when I was hypnotized,
you talked about me leaving...
Quiet.
Here she comes.
♪♪
You may sit. (chuckles)
BULLOCK: I'm just gonna say,
this isn't gonna be some
long, drawn-out, tearful affair
like you all are used to, okay?
This is gonna be
a short wedding.
I'm gonna try and make it
quick so we can all get to the bar.
- (laughter)
- Okay?
I first met a young Jim Gordon
when he was a, uh...
pain-in-the-ass, moralistic
- rookie detective.
- (laughter)
In the years since, he's
evolved into a pain-in-the-ass,
moralistic captain.
I'd say he's my best friend,
but in truth, he's
my only friend.
So we'll skip that.
Uh, on to Lee.
Lee's always had his back.
Except for the time
when she was infected
with the crazy-making
virus and she tried to kill him,
but that's love.
But I will say,
if there's one beautiful
thing that's happened
over these last few crazy years,
it's that these two
people met each other.
And that truly is...
a beautiful thing.
Jim, will you please
take Lee's hand?
(clears throat)
Do you, Jim Gordon,
take Lee Thompkins to be
your lawfully wedded wife,
to have and to hold,
from this day forward,
for better, for worse,
for richer, for poorer,
in sickness and in health,
to love and cherish
till death do you part?
I do.
And you, Lee Thompkins,
do you do the same?
Sure, Harvey.
I do.
By the power vested in me...
by absolutely no one...
(laughter)
I now pronounce you
husband and wife.
(cheering, whistling)
♪♪
What?
(applause fades)
And now Jim Gordon
and Lee Thompkins
are man and wife.
Thank God you held
the city together so that
this blessed event
could take place.
It was never gonna work.
What?
Controlling the gangs
was not a backup plan.
You... saw a chance
to convince James Gordon
that you had changed.
But he will never see you
as anything but a
dangerous woman
keeping his child from him.
Then I'd best be long gone
before he can do
anything about it.
He will hunt you till
the ends of the earth.
(chuckles)
Let him.